CIA people love, love, love to go watch
CIA movies. Not because they love
necessarily the CIA movies, but they
love to criticize them. Hi, I'm John
Kiriakou, former CIA officer. Today
we're going to break down scenes from
spy movies. This is the breakdown.
The Man from [music] U.N.C.L.E.
>> We'll leave you two to
get acquainted.
All right.
You're my hostage now.
>> I laugh because that's true. We always
overdo it. I worked for a station chief
one time who [clears throat]
had never been an operations officer.
She had been a paper pusher.
And they made her the chief of a big
station. There was some nuclear
scientist in town. She sent an all-hands
email around the station saying,
"Everybody's got to go try to recruit
this nuclear scientist. Figure out what
hotel he was staying in." And we went to
the the bar. Cuz where are you going to
go? You can't just like ask what room
he's in and go up to his room and invite
yourself in. So, we're all sitting in
bar. First of all, this nuclear
scientist was from a Muslim country. And
so, he's not going to be in the bar of
all places.
And as it turned out, every single seat
at every single table in the bar was
occupied by a CIA officer. And then when
we decided, "This guy's not going to
come in here for a drink." Literally
everybody in the bar got up at the same
time and walked out. And the whole thing
was a failure and an embarrassment.
>> What would motivate you to become the
CIA's most effective agents? I concluded
it must be to
counteract the humiliation of knowing
your balls are at the end of a very long
leash held by a very short man.
>> Yeah, I know that this movie was a
comedy and it was a lot of fun. But,
that's also
an accurate portrayal of uh of a hostile
operational meeting. We've all been in
meetings like that where you're trying
to intellectually one-up each other.
Maybe you'd like to recruit him. He'd
certainly like to recruit you. If you're
going to make a threat, you have to be
able to follow through on that threat.
But, these kinds of meetings, yes,
literally happen every single day.
>> [music]
>> The Night Manager.
>> If you're content, I suggest we process
the second half of the payment.
>> I'm entirely content.
>> Good.
>> Please check.
>> [music]
>> Thank you.
>> Pause here. This to me looks like a like
a clandestine transfer, goods for money.
Could be anything. Could be anything
from equipment to weapons to drugs.
Uh but, this
is normally how something like this
would happen. Let's skip ahead.
>> [music]
>> Jesus.
I want my money back, Mr. Roper.
>> And don't you hate when that happens? In
real life, no, there would never be a a
situation like that. It's It's In real
life, it's very anticlimactic.
Where you're going to exchange money for
the product, whatever the product
happens to be. Usually, the payment is
the easiest part of about a relationship
with the source. The source is perfectly
happy to give up whatever information he
or she has, perfectly happy to put his
hand out and take the payment. And nine
times out of 10, it's cash. And it's a
monthly retainer. So, there's really no
excitement involved in in making the
payment. Uh usually, it's just pro
forma. And you ask them to sign a
receipt and they could sign Bugs Bunny
if they want but just so long as there's
a receipt that's signed and you have to
deal with the accountants back at
headquarters. You know, I was once told
by a boss, you never want to mess with
medical,
security or finance because not only can
they ruin your career,
they can get you locked up and so you
want all the paperwork to be in order
especially when there's money involved.
>> [music]
>> Spy Kids
>> I'll take you to the safe house.
>> My parents can't be spies. They're not
cool enough.
>> That's cool.
>> Pause here.
There are certainly safe houses all over
the world. Every every intelligence
service in the world utilizes safe
houses. Sometimes jointly. There was
even a scene in the in the movie Munich
where the Israelis and the Jordanians
were in the same safe house although the
Jordanians had no idea that their
counterparts there were Israelis. But
yeah, there are absolutely safe houses.
Infrastructures like this. No, there are
no Batcaves or hidden layers. The
military is a different situation of
course.
They have hidden facilities all over the
planet but for the CIA
No. Let's fast forward. Unfortunately,
there are no high speed submersibles.
There are submersibles. There's one
that's even on display at the CIA
headquarters from from the Cold War. You
know, little one man submarines that you
can now buy in the Hammacher Schlemmer
catalog. Not for use today.
Not unless you're a member of drug
cartel.
Skyfall
>> [music]
>> I'd like to start with some simple word
associations. Just tell me the first
word that pops into your head. For
example, I might say day and you might
say wasted.
Agent.
Provocateur.
Woman. Provocatrice.
Heart.
Target.
>> Pause here.
Bond is undergoing a psych evaluation in
this in this scene. Something that every
intelligence officer has to go through.
You have to be sane in order to go
overseas and carry out these operations.
Just after the 9/11 attacks when
when one of the CIA counterterrorism
center branch chiefs approached me and
asked me if I would go overseas for a
short-term mission. And I said, "Yeah,
sure." I said, "Why don't you ask Dave
to go?
He covers this issue." And the chief
said, "Dave Dave went nuts. He didn't
pass the
the psych eval evaluation." So, I saw
Dave. I said, "Hey Dave, I'm going to go
to this country and do this operation. I
we should probably huddle and you can
brief me on it." I said, "Sorry to hear
you went nuts." And he said, "Yeah, what
are you going to do? It'll pass. I'll be
okay. I'll be back up and at them in in
6 months." I was like, "Okay, whatever."
I mean, I don't know how nuts he was. He
was clearly too nuts to go overseas.
Everybody does these psych evaluations.
You have them pre-employment. You have
one 3 years after you're hired and then
every 5 years for the rest of your life
unless you do something overseas that
requires maybe a little bit of
intermediate intervention. Like maybe
you beat the hell out of somebody at a
traffic stop or make a particularly
inexplicable stupid decision in an
operation. You're going to have to get
with the shrinks and and work it out
with them. Let's fast forward.
>> 007
Ticket to Shanghai.
Documentation and passport. Thank you.
And this.
Walther PPK/S 9 mm short.
There's a microdermal sensor in the
grip.
Encoded [music] to your palm print so
only you can fire it.
Less of a random killing machine, more
of a personal statement.
>> The location of this meetup appears to
be the Tate Gallery. Never, ever, under
any circumstances would such a meeting
take place in public because you
constantly run the risk of surveillance,
cameras, microphones. You run the risk
of some random tourist who happens to be
walking by hearing the conversation. You
would never have that conversation in
any public place. Even out in the open
in a park, you run the risk of of
parabolics, for example. This
conversation would always take place in
a vaulted area inside MI6 headquarters.
>> Standard issue radio transmitter.
>> That looked like kind of a big
transmitter compared to what I've seen
uh in the past. The transmitters can get
very small to the point where they're
they're more like chips, about the size
of a of a penny, but they are not
switchable on and off. They're always
transmitting, always sending out a ping.
In some extreme cases, you can even have
them implanted. You know, you have it
implanted in your shoulder or in your
butt crack or wherever it is that
somebody's not going to notice it. But
yeah, you're going to want a transmitter
in case you're kidnapped. In the 1980s,
the CIA station chief in Beirut, William
Buckley, was kidnapped and tortured
mercilessly to death. He had a
transmitter. It was embedded in his belt
buckle, and the very first thing the
kidnappers did was they took his belt
off and they left it in the parking
garage where he was kidnapped. Yeah, the
tech is out there. It's just a question
of implementing it.
Tenet.
>> [music]
>> Pause here.
It's almost unheard of for a CIA officer
to directly infiltrate a group,
especially a terrorist group. And it's
for a variety of reasons. You don't look
the role, you don't speak the language,
or if you do speak the language, you
speak it with an accent, usually an
American accent. So, what is normally
done is you recruit a person who's
either already in the group or is able
to penetrate the group. And then you
carry out your operations through that
person, through that cutout. So, to
switch badges on a uniform,
that's nothing that I've ever ever heard
of. Let's fast forward.
>> We live in a twilight world.
We live in a twilight world.
And there are no friends at dusk. You've
been made. The siege is a blind for them
to vanish you.
>> What we saw there was an exchange of
bonafides. That's something that is
very, very important and is taught
practically on the first day of
operational training. If you are
undercover or under deep cover, and no
one knows or even suspects that you're
an intelligence officer, and another
intelligence officer has to make contact
with you, there's going to be an
exchange of bonafides. So, if I break
into the room, I kick down the door, you
turn and look, and I have to say "The
rain in Spain falls mainly in the
plain." And then you respond with
"Mares eat oats and does eat oats and
little lambs eat ivy." We both know
that we're on the same team. But if one
side or the other doesn't know the
bonafides, then anything goes. It was
never, ever my experience that people
would panic and not remember the
bonafides. It's so drilled into you in
training. You almost can't forget. And
in addition, you have to remember that
people hired by intelligence services,
any intelligence service, especially in
an operational position, you have to be
somebody who has sociopathic tendencies,
right? You have to be very cool
undercover. There's kind of a famous
story of the astronaut Neil Armstrong
uh
taking over from Buzz Aldrin as they're
landing the Apollo module on the on the
surface of the moon. Buzz Aldrin's heart
was racing and he was afraid that he
would crash it into the surface of the
moon. And instead, Neil Armstrong took
over and NASA detected that as he was
getting closer to the surface of the
moon, his heartbeat actually slowed
down. That's not normal, but that's the
kind of person that an intelligence
service would want to recruit. Somebody
who not just is cool undercover, but is
is cool under pressure and becomes even
more cool under extreme pressure.
The Bourne Ultimatum
>> Get some rest, [music] man.
You look tired.
He's looking right at her.
>> [music]
>> This is a realistic scene. It's not
often that you're going to be so close
to a person that you're going to be able
to see them while you're talking to
them, but it does happen. One of the
things that they utilized here that's
very effective in real life operations
is out of the way places for static
surveillance. So, most people when they
think they might be under surveillance
or are concerned that they could be
under surveillance, they're looking
behind them. They're not looking up in
the second, third, 10th floor thinking,
you know, there's somebody with
binoculars up there. But frequently,
there are. And not just one person,
there's one person every block. A person
from five blocks back will run around
and assume a second static position.
That actually is common and it's a part
of training. Let's fast forward.
>> Where are you now?
>> I'm sitting in my office.
>> I doubt that.
>> And why would you doubt that?
>> If you were in your office right now,
we'd be having this conversation face to
face.
>> Breaking into offices was one of the
funnest things I ever did.
I enjoyed doing that very much. You
know, sometimes you just want to get
through the filing cabinet. Sometimes
it's longer term, you want to plant a
bug or a camera, although cameras were
unusual. But, yeah, breaking into an
office, sure, people do that ALL THE
TIME.
>> [music]
>> YEAH, WILSON, CHECK MY OFFICE.
>> REQUESTING picture of my office.
>> [music]
>> DAMN
>> WHAT'S GOING ON?
>> WE NEED BUILDING SECURITY UP HERE.
>> HE'S GOT EVERYTHING.
>> God damn it. At CIA headquarters, we
work in vaulted areas. So, the entire
vault, the entire office is considered a
vault. With the entire office being a
vault, you can just leave stuff out all
night long, 24 hours, not a problem.
Working in a satellite office, working
in a station, whether it's domestic or
foreign, nothing is considered to be an
open vault like it is at headquarters.
And so, if there's nobody in the office,
literally everything has to be locked
up. You remove your hard drive from the
computer, you put that in the safe. All
your paper files, and you try to keep
paper to an absolute minimum. That's all
kept in the safe. And the safe is one of
these like really heavy-duty steel
multiple reinforcement kind of, you
know, classified safe. Not like this
that you can just, you know, pick it and
steal files.
>> [music]
>> Agent Cody Banks.
>> Mary had a little lamb.
Its fleece is white as snow.
Peter Piper picked a peck of pickled
peppers.
>> Bubble gum, bubble gum in a dish.
>> How many pieces do you wish?
>> This is what happens when you design a
codebook at summer camp.
>> One of the things that that struck me
was the way Frankie Muniz smiles all the
time. He's so excited to be a part of
this operation. And that's exactly how
we were.
Uh the first time I ever went to the
Oval Office and there's the president,
the vice president, the National
Security Advisor, and the CIA Director.
I'm 25 years old and they are there to
listen to me and what I have to say. I
couldn't stop smiling and I couldn't
stop thinking my buddies from high
school would never believe in a million
years what I was doing right now.
There most certainly is a world where
children are recruited to be
intelligence officers. Not in the United
States, not anywhere in Western Europe
even or the Western world, but the
Russians have long had a program where
children are recruited as part of what
are called or what is called the
illegals program. In my own neighborhood
of Arlington, Virginia just two years
ago, a group of illegals was broken up
by the FBI. They were all arrested,
charged with espionage, and then traded
for American spies. Kind of like the old
Bridge of Spies idea from the Cold War.
They just sit for years
until their expertise is needed. There
was a television series on Netflix
called The Americans. It was 100% true
to life
in following a family in the illegals
program. And toward the end of the
series, the children were finally
activated. They were something like 16,
17 years old. But we wouldn't do it in
the United States. At the same time, the
Russians absolutely do.
>> Mission Impossible.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The dirty little secret of intelligence
operations is that almost all of the
tech that's used is just purchased on
Amazon.
It's easier, it's faster, and it's far
cheaper just to buy something that has
already been invented and manufactured
than to reinvent the wheel and start
from scratch.
Let's fast forward.
This is just so
unrealistic. It's very cool, and it's
very cool to see it, you know,
implemented, but in real life this stuff
just doesn't exist. You couldn't buy
that on Amazon. You might be able to get
a green screen for 20 bucks, but that's
about as close as you're going to come.
What would happen in real life is you
would spend 6 months working to recruit
the guard or recruit somebody close to
the guard so that you could get whatever
it is done that you needed to get done.
I have a big beef with 24.
Yeah, the silent helicopter gets you
every time. It's a good thing nobody
could hear that helicopter from 50 ft
away. You know, there are a lot of
shows, especially on regular broadcast
television, that just don't work. There
was one called Covert Affairs. Oh my
god, it was the worst CIA show I've ever
seen in my life, where this analyst just
walks into the Oval Office and says,
"Madam President, I need to take out a
hit on someone." It's like, first of
all, you're under arrest for just
barging into the Oval Office. Who Who do
you think you are, just walking into the
Oval Office like you own the place?
Secondly, you've just committed a felony
because according to Executive Order
12333, you can't order hits on anybody.
I hated that show. Another one, NCIS.
I'm sorry, I know a lot of people love
NCIS, but NCIS stands for Naval Criminal
Investigative Service. You can't be with
your guns out housing project in LA. You
only have jurisdiction on Navy bases
and on ships, not in the LA housing
projects with your gun up in the air
again to shoot somebody in the face.
It's the same thing with this. They're
at like the Rose Bowl or something
having a shootout in the Rose Bowl. Come
on, everybody's under arrest. You've all
committed felonies.
>> [music]
>> Burn Notice.
>> If you're going to put prints on a gun,
sticking it into somebody's hand isn't
going to do it. Any decent lawyer can
explain prints on a gun.
But try explaining prints on the inside
of the trigger assembly.
>> Oop.
I happen to be sitting next to the guy
who created and was the showrunner for
Burn Notice on a plane. We were all
going from Washington to LA. I never
talk to anybody on planes, but I was
sitting next to this guy, his name is
Matt Nix, an absolutely brilliant and
gifted writer and showrunner. We struck
up a conversation and I happen to be a
fan of Burn Notice. So, I said, "What do
you do for a living?" He said, "I
created a show." I said, "Oh, is it
something I might have heard of?" And he
said, "Well, maybe. It's It's the number
one show on basic cable. It's called
Burn Notice." I said, "Oh my god, I love
Burn Notice. I've watched every single
episode. In fact, I ran the credits in
slow motion
just to see who your script advisor
was." And I I see one. And he said, "Oh,
I've been obsessed with the CIA since I
was a kid. So, I've read every book and
I don't have a script advisor." By the
time we landed in LA, I was the script
advisor for season 6. And Matt and I are
still friends. So, some sometimes
writers
take this so seriously that they make it
100%
accurate.
>> [music]
>> Zero Dark Thirty.
>> If you thought there was some
secret cell somewhere working Al-Qaeda,
then I want you to know that you're
wrong.
This is it.
There's no working group coming to the
rescue.
There's nobody else hidden away on some
other floor.
>> I was the chief of one of the branches
inside the Counterterrorism Center. I
worked with her.
>> Just us.
>> She was actually my immediate boss. This
scene is accurate. Yes. And you have to
understand the frustration, too.
9/11 happened because we failed. 9/11
was the worst intelligence failure in
American history. It was worse than
Pearl Harbor. 3,000 Americans were
slaughtered on one day because we didn't
do our jobs. I'm surprised that his
language was as clean as it was. I will
say though about this film.
Zero Dark Thirty was a CIA propaganda
film. There was so much that was wrong
with this film in that the CIA Deputy
Director
and the CIA's Deputy Director for
Operations
gave Kathryn Bigelow, the director, and
Mark Boal, the writer, a classified
briefing
over a classified mock-up of the Osama
bin Laden house where bin Laden was
found and killed. That was violation of
the Espionage Act. The Director of the
CIA
Leon Panetta at the time invited Boal
and Bigelow to CIA headquarters for an
attaboy
speech in which he revealed the names of
the SEAL Team 6 members who killed Bin
Laden. That was a violation of the
Espionage Act. He later said that he
didn't realize they were in the
audience. So, no harm, no foul. When it
was revealed that they were in the
audience
the CIA's office of security went back
through his speech and ended up
redacting 27 lines of additionally
classified information. That was a
violation of the Espionage Act. But, the
worst part of this movie was that it
perpetuated the lie that the torture
program led to Osama bin Laden's
location.
It did not. If anything, the torture
program delayed
the finding of Osama bin Laden. What led
to Osama bin Laden's location was really
great analysis, not the lie that this
movie would have us believe.
>> When he wants to make a call, he leaves
the house, walks [music] a few blocks,
and switches on the phone.
We need to keep canvassing the
neighborhood until we find him.
>> We got a shooter.
>> Pause here.
>> Yeah, that's right out of
CIA counterterrorism training. Virtually
on your first day of CIA
counterterrorism training, you are put
in this situation where you're in a car
you're cut off, shooters cut you off,
you have a second to decide if you
should run them over and kill them, or
reverse and
as the CIA teaches you, get off the X,
or get out of the kill zone. Somebody
that close
I'd run them right over.
And then I'd back over them if I had to.
But yeah, that that is completely real
life. We've lost a lot of people over
the years
in situations like that.
Tom Clancy's Jack Ryan
>> Former Director Miller warned this
committee on several occasions about the
threat that President Udo presented.
>> Ideas that the acting director and I do
not share.
>> And yet, you cannot prove that we
weren't involved.
Doesn't that concern you?
>> No, sir.
It terrifies [music] me.
>> Very powerful.
And in a perfect world
that's true. We know though, of course,
that the CIA has been weaponized
repeatedly over the years by Democrats
and Republicans both. In a perfect
world, the CIA would exist only to serve
and protect the American people. But the
CIA has a way of pushing the envelope
and just waiting
for government to push back. And that's
not
a reliable strategy because it will keep
pushing and pushing and pushing until we
have a torture program and a secret
prison program and an illegal renditions
program and weaponization where they
take down their domestic enemies. The
reason why this happens is because we
don't have oversight like you're seeing
in this clip. We don't have members of
the House Permanent Select Committee on
Intelligence or the Senate Select
Committee on Intelligence Intelligence
who are willing to stand up. Instead,
and I regret to that I have to even say
this,
instead what we have on Capitol Hill are
members of both parties who are nothing
more than cheerleaders for the CIA. So,
to see a hearing like this where the CIA
is actively challenging the Deputy
Director
doesn't happen in real life. It should.
It should happen every day.
But it doesn't.
>> [music]
>> Argo
>> It's roadblocks.
>> I mean, wait till the weather clears up
then
>> the six bikes, provide them with maps to
the Turkish border.
>> We have intelligence they can ride
bicycles or we're prepared to send in
somebody to teach them.
>> Or you could just send in training
wheels and meet them at the border with
Gatorade.
>> Tony.
>> It's 300 miles to the Turkish border.
They need a support team following them
with a tire pump.
>> We were just asked to sharpshoot this.
State is handling the op.
>> I'm sorry, who is this?
>> Tony's an ex-fil specialist. He got a
lot of the Shah's people out after the
fall.
>> Sir, if these people can read or add,
pretty soon they're going to figure out
they're six short of a full deck.
It's winter. You can't afford to wait
around till spring so it's nice enough
to take a bike ride. The only way out of
that city is the airport.
>> This is absolutely accurate. Tony Mendez
is a giant in the history of the CIA.
His wife is a giant in the history of
the CIA and this is one of the greatest
operations that the CIA has ever carried
out in its history. It was Tony Mendez
who saved the hostages who had taken
refuge in the Canadian Embassy in Tehran
in 1979. Argo was a crazy idea but it
was once described to me as the least
likely to fail of all the crazy ideas.
And so they went with it. The original
idea to use bicycles was a terrible idea
because as he pointed out it was winter
time and nobody rides bicycles in the
winter time especially when you're going
north into the mountains where it's even
colder and with more snow. The idea that
that Tony came up with was to create a
fake sci-fi movie to be filmed in Iran
in the midst of the revolution and that
sounds like a nutty idea too but it
actually worked. These meetings are the
kinds of meetings where you can just say
the craziest thing and if
people deem it to be even
remotely possible, they'll give it real
consideration. With that said, usually
the the operations with the fewest
moving parts are the ones that are most
likely to succeed.
>> [music]
>> The good shepherd.
First of all, certainly [music] books
like that exist. They're called CDs or
concealment devices. There are some CDs
[music] that you're just assigned. Like,
here are some CDs for you. Use them for
whatever you want to use them for. Some
are big enough you can put a gun in. So,
yeah, absolutely they exist and every
[music] CIA officer has access to them.
The part where he's looking at the copy
of Ulysses is a little
a little bit Hollywood fabulist in that
he's looking for an anomaly in the
placement of the book. And it was placed
just ever so slightly differently from
all of the other books. It looks like,
you know, this is a collection of of
really classic um pieces of literature,
but the binding was different. It was
newer on Ulysses and it was just sitting
up ever so slightly higher than the
other books. And so, it looked like
somebody had been handling that book.
When he took it off the shelf, he was
looking for an anomaly in the hard cover
just to see if something had been glued
or maybe there was something inside. He
could tell that there was. Frankly, it
wasn't a very good concealment device if
you can feel it with your finger, but he
could feel it with his finger and then
he knew to go into it.
>> I just wanted to hear something from you
that was true.
He was careless.
>> FBI, you're under arrest. Stand up.
>> It's not outside the realm of
possibility that he would have
confronted somebody directly like that.
And unfortunately, you know, over the
last
30 years, this has happened a number of
times. The traitor Aldrich Ames, the
traitor Robert Hanssen. One was a CIA
counterintelligence officer, the other
was the chief of FBI
counterintelligence. And here they were
both working for the Russians. Can you
imagine? The chief of CIA
counterintelligence and FBI
counterintelligence both working for the
Russians. So, it happens every once in a
while. On the other side of that, we
talked earlier about the Russian
illegals program. I know an illegal, a
former illegal.
Uh he was trained in East Germany, sent
here as a sleeper. He settled in
Brooklyn, lived in Brooklyn for 20
years, uh did what he was supposed to
do, just get a job as a normal American
would, didn't speak with any kind of an
accent, but he fell in love with a
woman. And they got married, and they
had a little girl. And he told me as
soon as he saw that baby for the very
first time, he knew he could never go
back. One day,
he was activated, and he didn't respond
to the activation.
And so, he's on the subway one day,
right here in New York. And he said the
subway didn't have very many people on
it, but this guy walked right up to him,
grabbed the strap, leaned over, and
said, "You know that if you don't go
home, I'm going to have to kill you."
And he said, rather than go to his
destination, he went directly to the
FBI's New York field office. And he
said, "I am a KGB sleeper. I've been
activated, and I don't want to go home."
And now he lives here in New York with
his wife. His daughter's in her 20s. The
Russians never tried to kill him, but,
you know, sometimes things like this
happen.
>> [music]
>> Captain America: The Winter Soldier.
Robert Redford was in Captain America?
>> What are you doing?
>> She's disabling security protocols and
dumping all the secrets onto the
internet.
>> Including Hydra's.
>> And Shield's.
>> If you do this, none of your past is
going to remain hidden.
>> Are you sure you're ready for the world
to see you as you really are?
>> Are you?
>> Ed Snowden kind of did it. Joshua
Schulte kind of did it. There are
catches in place now to make sure that
information is compartmentalized to the
point that nobody else can do it. I
would
offer up my own personal opinion that
what Ed Snowden did was was heroic and
was bonafide whistleblowing. What he
released was the fact that NSA and CIA
were spying on us, on Americans. In
today's day and age,
you can't go to just one computer system
and just download the crown jewels of
the CIA or the broader intelligence
community. It's just not possible.
Nobody has that kind of access. Nobody.
When I got out of prison, I served 23
months in prison for blowing the whistle
on the CIA's torture program. When I got
out of prison, I was invited to a dinner
at the Greek Ambassador's residence. And
I went there to the dinner and I saw a
member of the Senate Select Committee on
Intelligence. And he walked over to me
and he said, "Hey, welcome home.
Congratulations." And I said, "Senator,
I I have to be honest with you. I
expected more from you. I expected some
support." And he got angry and he said,
"Look,
it took all of my energy just to not
lose my security clearance." And I said,
"Oh, you're afraid of them. I thought
you were the overseer." They're all like
that now. They're just cheerleaders.
>> [music]
>> Kingsman
Let's skip ahead.
The training is tough, but it's not that
tough.
>> [music]
[laughter]
>> Uh, no.
No, listen, training was a challenge. I
learned skills that I never even
imagined existed. I was proud of what I
ended up doing in
in training, but there was nothing like
that. But, you're never going to find
yourself in a position like this where
you're going to need to Listen, you need
to think on your feet, certainly. I'll
give you one example. We were in We were
in driving training and we had to drive
a car through this
kind of no man's land that was supposed
to be in like the Middle East or Africa
or something like that, Central Asia.
And the instructors remotely shut off my
engine. And then my car just went dead.
I was like, "What the heck? The car just
went dead. Like the battery maybe or
whatever."
And then somebody opens fire on me with
paint balls.
So, they're hitting the car. I take my
seat belt off. I crawl across, get out
on the other side. I'm laying flat on
the ground. I pull out my gun. I look to
see where the shots are coming from. And
it's actually a robot that's in a van.
The the side sliding door of the van is
open and the robot is firing these paint
balls at me. So, I'm shooting back at
the robot and I can't get a clean shot
at it. I pop up just a little bit. I
shoot out my own windows and then I'm
able to shoot the robot and disable it.
And the instructors come out and they
said, "Damn it, Kiriakou. That was the
last decent car we had." I said, "I
couldn't get a clean shot. You're the
one who told me get off the X, get out
of the kill zone. I couldn't shoot the
robot from the angle that I was. You
should have cut my engine off later or
earlier or something. What do you want
me to do?" That's training. This is
Hollywood. Thanks for having me, GQ.
We'll do this again. In the meantime,
check out my podcast, John Kiriakou's
Dead Drop, on Apple Podcasts.